Bardacke, Gregory; Papers apap405
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Gregory Bardacke Papers
1937-1938
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap405
.2 cubic ft.
This collection contains material related to Gregory Bardacke's work as a labor organizer for the International Ladies' Garment Worker's Union (ILGWU) and about the Derby Sportswear factory strike which began in August 1937 in Herkimer, New York.
Content Description
This collection contains newspaper clippings, legal materials, correspondence, and photographs related to Gregory Bardacke's work as a labor organizer for the International Ladies' Garment Worker's Union (ILGWU) in Herkimer, New York. In particular there are materials related to the Derby Sportswear factory strike in Herkimer which began in August 1937.
Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
All items in this collection were donated by Ann Bardacke, daughter of Gregory Bardacke, in 2023 and 2024.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is arranged alphabetically.
Biographical Note
Gregory Joseph Bardacke was born in 1912 in Harbin, China, the second child of Joseph and Anya Bardacke. His parents, both Jewish, were Russian speakers from Ukraine and Lithuania respectively, and Bardacke spoke only Russian until he attended school in Canada (where the family had moved when he was about a year old) at age five. The family immigrated to the United States in 1921. Bardacke graduated from high school in New Jersey and attended Syracuse University on a football scholarship (though he only played for Syracuse for one year, choosing to play semi-pro as he needed the money for rent and food). Thus, although he earned a degree (in Chemistry), he was not actually awarded the degree as the University claimed he owed money for tuition.
Bardacke began working as an organizer for the International Ladies' Garment Worker's Union (ILGWU) in early 1937 in Herkimer, New York hoping to organize the employees of the Derby Sportswear factory to form a union. In August 1937, some employees at the factory went on strike. During the strike, Bardacke was arrested and indicted several times for defending the young female workers, but he was never convicted. After leaving the ILGWU, Bardacke worked for the Hatters Union in Connecticut.
In January 1939, Bardacke married Beatrice Schonberg, another labor organizer. Although both he and his wife had earlier been members of the Socialist Party, when Hitler invaded Poland, they quickly joined the Democratic Party and Bardacke raised money from workers in labor unions for the Party. The two remained committed Democrats their entire lives. Before World War II ended, Bardacke took a job with the War Production Board in Washington D.C., working with labor unions to support the war effort. He then worked at Dymaxion Dwelling Machines, Inc. Bardacke next worked with R. Buckminster Fuller at Dymaxion Dwelling Machines, Inc. (later renamed Fuller Houses, Inc.) and then the Lustron Corporation. Both companies sought to build pre-fabricated homes, given the post-war demand for housing.
In 1947, Bardacke was appointed the labor representative to the United Nations Appeal for Children (later UNICEF). In 1953, he began working as the Executive Director of the Histadrut, the Israeli Labor Federation, out of its New York office. Bardacke worked there, connecting the leadership of American labor unions with their counterparts in Israel, for the rest of his working career.
Bardacke died in 1991, survived by three daughters.
Bardacke, Gregory, 1912-1991; I.L.G.W.U. (International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union); Strikes and lockouts--New York (State); Herkimer (N.Y.); Labor; Labor union meetings; News Clippings
- Account of Derby Sportswear Workers and Unionization, ca. 1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Agreement Between Derby Sportswear and the International Ladies' Garment Worker's Union, 1937 July 15 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Derby Sportswear Court Case, Transcript of Stenographer's Minutes, 1937 October 25 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Herkimer Strike Letter, Clippings, and Photograph, 1937-1938; Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Indictments Arising Out of Derby Sportswear Strike, 1938 April 30 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Letter from Harold Beer to Gregory Bardacke, 1938 May 30-1938 May 31 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Memorandum of Decisions, 1937 September 3 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- News Clippings, 1937-1938; Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Notice from Eva S. Jacobs to Gregory Bardacke, 1937 November 4 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- The People of the State of New York vs. Gregory Bardacke, Theresa Manino, and Rosie Licari, 1937 August 13; 1937 August 20-1937 August 21; 1937 August 23 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Photographs, 1937; Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Special Meeting Notice to the International Ladies' Garment Worker's Union, Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- United States of America Before the National Labor Relations Board, 1937 September 16 (Box 1, Folder 13)